[Music]
it's your wife meditations on Leonard
Cohen number 15 young young young she
said that's a quote from Leonard Cohen
death of a ladies man
like Shakespeare Bob Dylan who
incidentally compared himself to
Shakespeare in his Nobel acceptance
letter Leonard Cohen and perhaps all
great metaphysical lyrical or symbolic
poets was tormented by a certain dark
lady so who is the dark lady in Cohen in
biblical traditions the dark lady is
Lilith in Hinduism she is Kali in
Cohen's cosmology perhaps we can say she
is the gypsy wife the gypsy wife is not
the nurturing feminine obviously but the
dark woman who would destroy the world
the Bible says Lilith wants to be on top
and sex in other words she wants control
and Dominion she will flee from the man
instead of spiritually marrying him of
course feminists might object that is
usually the man who wants to be on top
and dominate but that's another issue
feminists might object to the Dark Lady
archetype is being fundamentally
negative view of women but that doesn't
mean that the femme fatale archetype
doesn't exist whether we like it or not
the women destroyer is everywhere in
traditional culture just as the man
destroyer is certainly there is much to
be learned from this dark fiery Lilith
she is an essential part of existence
the gypsy wife might destroy us or help
us find redemption not by following her
but by letting her go the gypsy wife is
the one who cannot be tamed
she puts a man on the threshing floor
she gives him a vision of hell anyone
who has been married to a gypsy wife as
I have been knows that her infidelity is
the ultimate test for a man but if he
becomes the
on her he tries to possess her she will
destroy him there is a reason why her
vagina has teeth she's not an invention
of the patriarchy but a reality of
nature the mother who devours her
children of course there is the Gypsy
husband too so all is fair in love and
war in fact the man will have to be a
gypsy to tango with her she will not be
tamed by the domestic man if the man
gives his allegiance to her she will
devour him like the female praying
mantis again we can also say that the
Gypsy wife if man survives her will
bestow magical powers will make him much
more immune to the darkness part of our
spiritual quest is meeting her which is
also the shock of spiritual growth the
Gypsy man and the Gypsy woman are man
and woman apart they are our separate
state of course we're not talking about
gypsy culture here but the wandering man
woman archetype they are the wound the
crack the duality at the heart of a
fallen world the homicidal bitching that
goes down in every kitchen as Cohen puts
it in democracy they represent the dark
face of God as Rebecca describes it and
according to mythical traditions we have
to descend to that chaos in darkness to
repair the face of God you cannot marry
the gypsy wife really she has nobody's
wife
we shouldn't invite that dark lady into
our hearts but pray that she is
dissolved that she will flee that she
will arrest would be an idiot to try to
embrace Kali she would tear us to pieces
and there was a reason why she wears a
necklace of severed heads better feed
her voracious hunger in another way
through which will magic or a song if
you have met the gypsy wife you will
know what I mean she will have shown you
the Gypsy husband your own darkest
nature it's a good thing to have
survived such a marriage
but I wouldn't wish it on anyone power
in the pit meditations on Leonard Cohen
number 16 and here I quote part of a
song called had to go crazy to love you
had to go crazy to love you had to go
down to the pit had to do time in the
tower begging my crazy to quit poetry
itself is a kind of divine craziness a
shortcut beyond linear thinking the poet
will evade conventional language he has
a certain contempt for the philosophers
though he also loves and makes use of
them his words are alive but not
reasonable
he speaks in metaphors little bombs of
light which explode the mind caught an
explanation and false logic he speaks
the language of the heart the most
deadly and effective poison to destroy
the ordinary paralysis that most of us
humans are caught in had to go crazy to
love you you who were never the one my
chase through the souvenir heartache her
braids and her blouse all undone the
poet goes down to the pit to rescue the
beloved damsel who has been trapped
there for centuries he must climb down
from his tower of abstraction and go
underground it's actually his own soul
it rescues down down there in the
hellish clown House of false mirrors in
the entrapment of egos and personalities
for the soul is she when Dante meets
Satan he meets his own ego monster not
someone outside and Beatrice is his own
soul his own divine form had to go crazy
to love you had to let everything fall
had to be people I hated had to be no
one at all rather than straightforward
aloof morality we can dance with these
clowns or subpersonalities to be fully
human is to be fully crazy in a divine
sense crazy enough to live through the
vista toots of the tower and the pit
when one meets Beatrice or Susanne one
is drawn into that feminine world of
madness her braids and her blah
done the braids and the blouse are the
entrapments that can seal the nakedness
of reality the erotic and Cohen is
always aligned with the sacred the
sacred is found near to madness love is
close to madness
why because one loses boundaries in love
the man-woman Union is the sacred inner
chamber where the ego surrenders and the
divine world is restored
not just in sex but in the whole cosmic
domain the ego will resist tooth and
nail going stark raving mad in the
process but when duality collapses in
love the soul is born sometimes I'd head
for the highways I'm old and the mirrors
don't lie but crazy has places to hide
in that are deeper than any goodbye we
live out our lives lost in the mirrors
of self our body decays and the divine
spark remains hidden unborn we try to
say goodbye to that world but go running
back and forth between the tower and the
pit idiotically begging for more
craziness we may rationalize our
failures and addictions we may think
that everything is going great but crazy
is waiting for us in the shadows this
crazy love is too painful to bear but
too pleasurable to resist like a woman
in her full power over us she unleashes
all of our craziness to liberate us from
that craziness she brings us home not to
her world but to the greater one the
sisters of mercy are themselves only
signs are doorways to infinity they
point to that beyond which is
paradoxically the most intimate and near
the sisters of mercy are not departed or
gone you who were never the one this is
the primordial mistake to try to possess
contain the beloved to mistake her for
Eden we must not get lost in her but
raise her up out of the underworld into
light in sentience
if we survive that terrible law that
underworld we learn compassion until we
can feel the hell that is heaven
heaven that is hell we remain trapped in
the either the tower or the pit the
tower is the lofty but sterile place of
separative man the pit is a biological
and mechanical world of separative woman
the reason cohen songs are so resonant
is that there is so much beneath the
surface suzanne is not just a dancer
from montreal she is like a fleshy
doorway but you have to go crazy to love
her to pass over her threshold to touch
her perfect body with your mind you have
to have your banality burned up in a
spiritual and visionary bonfire when one
is tired of fighting in the tower or
down in the pit then one gives up the
struggle and the blessings of the
non-dual world descend
I'm tired of choosing desire I've been
saved by a blessed fatigue that give
gates of commitment unwired and nobody
trying to leave the crack and everything
meditations on Leonard Cohen number 17
Cohen has said that an essential artist
has only one thing to say one obsession
perhaps we can say that for Cohen this
was and the lyric that summarizes his
Testament most completely there is a
crack in everything that's how the light
gets in this crack and everything is his
whole philosophy it covers the whole
territory from the bedroom to the
geopolitical arena from the hidden
chambers of the heart to the porn movie
of contemporary civilization I suspect
Cohen gave up writing novels and poetry
too for the most part because he found
the ballad to be the perfect vehicle to
express this everything there is
something essential Cohen aims for that
suits the ballad perfectly it is the
formal language of longing not just for
the beloved but for transcendence the
bard sings of the ordinary human drama
in larger spiritual terms he joins the
sublime and the mundane the complexities
of love to the simple the spit to the
starlight one of his last songs make it
real is a touching confession of how
without the beloved to animate our
existence the world is just a cavity a
scream an empty shell a dark and
meaningless
she or the Holy Spirit breaks us into
and paradoxically this brokenness this
crack and everything allows us to lift
the veil and see the beloved's face and
see the wild perfumes and secrets all in
view or that primordial transmission
that Rhian chants the world the
troubadour must make some gesture of
devotion to liberate those burning
hearts in hell you must acknowledge a
higher will as in the song if it be your
will in each moment word by word thought
by thought
we choose our allegiances to the reified
dark world or flowers made of stone or
transcendence flowers made of light we
can let illuminated wisdom heal us or
choose to inhabit a darkness or no one
that we hurt could ever heal what could
be a worse hell than that at times we
need to gaze into that hell so that the
possibility of liberation joy and
secrets all of you emerge the beloved
shows us the way back to a world that is
real first through a journey to the
underworld you is also thou the holy
other it's not just the opposite sex but
every leaf flower fragile instance of
appearance they all sing the same song
if the stars were all unpinned and a
cold and bitter wind swallowed up the
world without a trace oh well that's
where I would be what my life would seem
to me if I couldn't lift the veil to see
our face different sides meditations on
Leonard Cohen number 18 we find
ourselves on different sides of a line
that nobody drew at all maybe one to the
higher I down here where we live it is -
that's from the out song different sides
from the album old ideas in 2012
Leonard Cohen has an amazing ability to
go buying humor and theology sex and
religion he is appropriately
unappropriate for humorless times a
sense of humor in Cohen is never far
from a deadly serious consideration we
can weep and laugh simultaneously while
listening to his songs while we take sex
than the religion far too seriously
Cohen provides the Jewish medicine a
good belly laugh at the games of the
world of course he knew that the games
of the world are essentially related to
sex and God sexual anxiety is our usual
condition
Freud knew that civilizations
discontents come from this feeling of
separation from the intimate other
however unlike Freud Cohen kept a higher
I in mind he did not attribute
everything to rationality and sex but
saw the humor in the sacred and in
sexual devotion I don't think people
would have been able to swallow Cohen's
earnestness if he didn't have a great
sense of wit and humor the sweetness in
those lyrics is what makes this bitter
pill go down and gives us the courage to
face more difficult truths there is a
spiritual family told us down in the
valley the famine goes on the famine up
on the hill but then he changes register
you want to change the way I make love I
want to leave it alone listening to us
sound like different sides is a profound
relief it tells us yes we are on
different sides but God is laughing so
we should never lose our sense of humor
or we are totally lost because that
humor is real universality and
emancipation this humor is not a cheap
kind of shrug or a mocking cynicism but
the kind that unifies us profoundly and
seeing both the ridiculousness of our
ego and the beauty of the divine
everybody knows that a totalitarian
world is built on humorless nests
totalitarian societies all begin with
some kind of utopian vision and
murder somewhere along the line people
lose their humanity in other words their
humor this is why humour may be more
effective than anything else against the
collective powers of darkness which
always veered dangerously towards real
fascism I don't know many others who can
combine profundity and humor in such a
way cohen writes in one moment words
that sound almost like Scripture the
pull of the moon the thrust of the Sun
and thus the ocean is crossed the waters
are blessed while a shadowy guests
Kindles the light for the lost and then
the next moment we have amok we have
pure lightness come on baby give me a
kissed up writing everything down as a
songwriter I don't know how he does this
actually it's a mystery to me if I knew
how to do it I I would do it myself when
I try to be too humorous than a song it
sounds trite it's this balance of
gravity and light that Cohen does better
than anybody a Cohen song restores the
humors and his antic do't to our egos
fascism popular problems meditations on
Leonard Cohen number 19 when I first
heard the album popular problems it did
nothing for me I liked the title and a
couple of its songs but I put it aside
considering it to be one of Leonard
Cohen's lesser works listening to it
soon after his death I see that I was
wrong it may take time to appreciate
this work of understated beauty to
discover a hallelujah in that album but
there is no hurry these songs will last
longer than those garbage bags the time
cannot decay as Cohen sings in democracy
Leonard Cohen's other albums various
positions was similarly understated and
underrated but now songs like hallelujah
if it be your will are part of the very
landscape delayed punchline again coin
makes big gestures by staying small and
intimate he seduces by being nearly
invisible sounds big
by playing quietly accesses deep feeling
by avoiding vulgar emotion
he slays melodrama by humor destroys
banality by paradox you got me singing
even though it all went wrong his
philosophical pessimism is paradoxically
the cause for joy we sing the Hallelujah
him though it is all going to hell in a
bucket if this attitude is not nihilism
precisely the material world is doomed
but our spirit can be indestructible the
awful truth that isn't worth a damn he
sings in democracy it being the sexual
political religious games of the world
this is something that no young person
can accept but an older person must
confess in order to approach higher
spiritual truths the Coens still sings
you got me singing celebrating love even
as we drive the nails into the cross of
our existence over and over again Cohen
gives us affirmation in the midst of
negation the ability to see both sides
of life if we speak about the glory of
God we ignore the dark God or the
left-hand-side of God that Rabbi Yaakov
speaks of who could stand beside you so
close to Eden when you glint it in every
eye and held the razor high shivering
every ram and son to a teacher the truth
holds a razor blade stands between Eden
and hell cuts away the superfluous
unites both the light and the dark
all of our popular problems are born in
the inherent separation of the light and
the dark man in women order and chaos
etc Cohen was an adult artist in a pop
culture landscape of babies rock and
roll has been mostly for young people
and young people are supposed to be
somewhat narcissistic it's part of their
development and yet to be adults we need
to slay the beast of narcissism Leonard
did that later in life and one gets a
sense that instead of degenerating into
cynicism he evolved into spaces of
greater joy
today the big popular problem might be
this narcissistic boy on the imperial
throne the ego anointed king but all the
more reason to imbibe the works of a
mature artist who can see through the
horrors of egos plastic creations
tell me again Leonard tell me over and
over again there is no God in heaven and
there is no hell below so says the great
professor of all there is to know the
professor of all there is to know as
Socrates new doesn't know anything nor
does he know that he doesn't know he
makes false conclusions based on his ego
and not divine creation I see the ghost
of culture with numbers on his wrist
salutes some new conclusion that all of
us have missed and yet the chains are
gone from heaven the storms are wild and
free now that's a song worth listening
to leaving the table meditations on
Leonard Cohen number 20 Leonard Cohen
songs offer a world of symbols the tower
the pit the hill the Beast the pillar
the naked woman the master the stone the
altar to name a few like a tarot deck
many of his images have a biblical or
occult route for instance one symbol
that appears often in cone songs is the
table what does that mean what does that
symbolize I'm leaving the table I'm out
of the game Cohen sings at the end of
his life but the table is also a place
of beginnings as well as endings we
leave the table to retire from the game
but come to the table to meet it is a
space where kin and kind gather or peace
where peace treaties are made where war
is declared across the old piece of oak
we gaze at each other in love or enmity
and harmony or indifference the table is
the epicenter of our home it's the line
that keeps heaven and earth
man and woman together and rooted it is
the neutral ground that guards our
civilization from chaos it is a place to
share our hearts and souls and make
prayers and recriminations the table
provides the necessary distance for a
civilized encounter it is where lovers
meet and depart the table is the beloved
oak plank where we suck drink pass our
lives share our bread and our time
together in civilized harmony but it is
also the place where the worldly poker
game goes on we're a boogie Street
samsara exists a table is where we bond
negotiate our love affair our marriage
Cornette some interesting things to say
about marriage incidentally here's a
quote I think marriage is the hottest
furnace of the spirit today what's more
difficult than solitude much more
challenging for people who want to work
on themselves it's a situation in which
there is no there are no alibis
excruciating most of the time but it's
only in this situation that any kind of
work can be done naturally I feel
ambiguous about it we feel ambiguous
about coming to the table because it is
safer to remain untouched we are
terrified for good reason to be bound to
that table of responsibilities but the
table is where we get our soul work done
there are many images of the sacrificial
table or altar and Cohen songs the
biblical story of Abraham sacrificing
Isaac haunts Cohen very deeply it seems
it comes up often like in song for Isaac
in The Butcher Cohen asks what kind of
tyrant God brings death into the world
and asked us to kill our only son the
table is a place where these hard
questions are posed where hard choices
are made where contracts are signed with
gods and spirits and men did I ever
leave you was I ever able or are we
still leaning across the old table Cohen
sings so touchingly hear an old man and
the reverie of a beloved who was gone
but who still appears forever gazing and
affection across the old table the table
is a ground where we lay out our hearts
for each other
where
we gather for intimacy and conversation
away from the storms and slaughters of
our daily lives to jest to drink and
fall into each other's eyes
when qohen sings I'm leaving the table
does this suggest Jesus at the Last
Supper it wouldn't have been the first
time coin has identified with Christ and
so long Marianne he's saying you held on
to me like a crucifix the table the
place of terrible goodbyes also as a
sweetness cohen sings little by little
for cutting the cord we're spending the
treasure oh no no that love cannot
afford i know you can feel it the
sweetness restored at the table we say
goodbye but the sweetness never leaves
like the perfume of a song sometimes
we're bound to that table with a bright
blade above us and only the nameless
grace to save us
sometimes the table is covered in the
blood of our slaughter the madness of
our words our dead children wrapped in
cloth sometimes we lie in the operating
table and our numbed with an anesthetic
waiting for the scalpel but at other
times the table is covered with flowers
and fine wine and high laughter and the
knowledge of eternity can we say then
that we meet at God's table Alexandre
leaving meditations on Cohan on Leonard
Cohen number 21 Leonard Cohen has been
saying goodbye for a long time in fact
we could say that most of his songs are
about leaving in one way or another just
a few titles illustrate my point hey
that's no way to say goodbye so long
Marianne Alexandra leaving leaving the
table closing time the list goes on and
on in fact his last album you want it
darker he's entirely about that final
curtain call and his own departure from
Earth maybe we can see all his songs and
so many other good songs revolve around
a kind of death spiritual or otherwise
after all death is our biggest concern
in life followed by sex perhaps
even in the orgy astok flush of life
where the woman tear their blouses off
from the men dance on the polka dots
there is the taste of death the chill
and the beauty of impermanence take this
waltz it's been dying for years he says
there's a bar where the boys have
stopped talking they've been sentenced
to death by the blues here a Cohen
navigates the desolation row of Dylan
and the wasteland of Eliot where those
sentenced to death and decay mingle with
youth and energy make more sad said the
Zen Roshi wants to Cohen in the studio
as if his songs weren't already
legendarily said and it isn't Cohen's
type of sad actually uplifting because
it releases us from sadness just as
happy music is so often depressing
because it diverts us from our deeper
concerns most people would rather listen
to The Beatles than Leonard Cohen
because it's happy music but happy music
starts to great after a while that's
because if a person is past 30 years old
he or she will have had to say a bitter
goodbye more than once will have had to
contemplate sickness old age and his or
her eventual extinction the wise learned
to hold light and darkness together not
to pit them against each other
Cohen never never separates death from
life or love from loss that is the depth
of the songs that is why they are so
nourishing in crisis and transition if
we have a deep sense of existence we can
see that every hello is also a goodbye
and yet it's also true that every
goodbye is hello so there's no need to
be suicidally depressed and one of his
most beautiful songs
Alexandra leaving Cohen sings say
goodbye to Alexandra leafing say goodbye
to Alexandra lost not only does coin say
goodbye to Alexandra he says goodbye to
saying goodbye
Alexandra leaving is the crucifix
uncrossed or life energy returned to
that bright source where there is no
leaving and Alexandra can paradoxically
ever be lost still even though they are
forever formless Li entwined this
doesn't make the leaving less poignant
Cohen and his lover are upheld by the
simplicity of pleasures and simple joys
he is full of appreciation for earthly
incarnation I'm quoting here upheld by
the simplicity of pleasure they gain the
light they farm lessly in twine and
radiant beyond your wildest measure they
fall among the voices and the wine and
so we say goodbye to Alexandra and
Leonard Cohen to enter that tiny spark
of a Zdenek light that is radiant beyond
your wildest measure these are songs of
faith and longing not despair
may they go on and on until love itself
is gone